Guide to the Womynspace Records
University of Houston Libraries
Womynspace Records
1973-1990
2007-013
Womynspace (Organization: Houston, Tex.)
0.50 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The Womynspace Records is housed in 1 box and consists of 3 series: Organizational Information, Equal Rights Amendment (ERA) and Disarmament Movement. This collection documents organizational meetings, events and goals. Additionally, these records include material from the 1970s and 1980s collected by the organization regarding Pro- and Anti- ERA sentiments, ERA ratification deadline extension Senate Hearings and the Disarmament Movement.
Historical Note:
Womynspace, Inc was a non-profit organization designed by and for women. Founded in 1985, it was directed by a collective of five women: Anita Davidson, Lynda Jones, Margo Shelton, Glena Stephenson and Rebecca Tallman. The organization operated under four basic tenets regarding the purpose of its existence. First and foremost, it sought to provide a gathering and healing place for women only. It provided space for artists and relief to women who were exploited as consumers. Lastly, it strived to add dimension to the “womyn’s” community. The organization also worked to establish an alternative living space in a communal setting; a coffeehouse that would provide artistic and gathering space; a shop and gallery space where “womyn” wares would be displayed and sold; a meeting and workshop space; and a forum for disseminating information throughout the womyn’s community.
Source Unknown
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Womynspace (Organization: Houston, Tex.)
Genre/Form of Material:
Brochures; Pamphlets; Publications (document genre); Records (documents)
Topical Term:
Feminism; Nonprofit organizations -- Texas -- Houston; Women -- Societies and clubs -- Texas -- Houston
Acquisition Information:
Donated by Margarette "Margo" Shelton September 16, 2006
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Related Materials:
Houston Gorilla Girls Records(http://archon.lib.uh.edu/index.php?p=collections/controlcard&id=468)
Scope and Contents
The Womynspace Records is housed in 1 box and consists of 3 series: Organizational Information, Equal Rights Amendment (ERA) and Disarmament Movement. This collection documents organizational meetings, events and goals. Additionally, these records include material from the 1970s and 1980s collected by the organization regarding Pro- and Anti- ERA sentiments, ERA ratification deadline extension Senate Hearings and the Disarmament Movement.
Detailed List of Contents
- Organizational Information
  - Notes regarding organization purpose, vision and goals, 1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Meeting agenda and minutes, 1985, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Non-profit Incorporation papers, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Womynspace calendar/ newsletter, 1985, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Equal Rights Amendment (ERA)
  - General
    - ERA information and history (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Articles, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - ERA mscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Organizational Pro-ERA Material, 1973-1981, undated
    - ERAmerica (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - National Federation of Business and Professional Women’s Clubs (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - League of Women Voters (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Common Cause (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - National Organization for Woman (NOW) (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Women Today (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Christian Feminists (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Religious Committee for the ERA (RCERA) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Catholics Act for ERA (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Additional brochures and pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Organizational Anti-ERA Material, 1974-1977, undated
    - Operation Wake Up (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Catholic Daughters of America (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - National Council of Catholic Women (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Daughters of the American Revolution (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - The Phyllis Schlafly Report (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Additional brochures (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - ERA Ratification Deadline Extension Senate Hearings
    - Testimonies, August 2, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Testimonies, August 3, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Testimonies, August 4, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence and articles (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Disarmament Movement
  - Pro-Disarmament material (Box 1, Folder 29)